the sum of the first n positive integers
can be represented by a triangular array
of dots as pictured the first row has
one dot and the nthrow has n dots we can
also add the N plus first row like this
where there are n plus one dots now we
can build a one-to-one correspondence
between the dots in the Triangular array
representing the sum of the first n
positive integers and pairs of dots in
the N plus first row the dot in Row 1
maps to the pair of dots in row N plus
one that are n units apart the two dots
in row two map to the two pairs in row
one plus one that are n minus one units
apart this process continues all the way
down until we see the dots in row N
correspond to the pairs of dots in row N
plus one that are one unit apart sure
enough we've mapped to every possible
pair of two dots in row N plus one
therefore the sum of the first and
positive integers must be n plus one
choose two which is n plus one times n
divided by two